{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man described Monck Mason’s miraculous three-day trip across the Atlantic in a balloon\nin a hoax article printed in the New York Sun. In a story by this man, an imprisoned man rubs\nrancid meat on his tied up hands and is saved from death by rats, and later again by Napoleon’s\nGeneral Lasalle [luh-sall]. He wrote a story whose narrator murders an old man with a “vulturelike” eye and confesses after hearing a sound from underneath the floorboards. For 10 points,\nname this author of “The Pit and the Pendulum” and “The Telltale Heart.”",
      "answer": [
        "Edgar Allan Poe",
        "Poe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A character in a Mark Twain novel describes this sport as “picturesque and ridiculous.” This\nsport’s name is derived from the Latin word meaning “to approach” or “to meet.” The French\nWars of Religion were partially triggered by Henry II’s death from this activity. The equipment\nused by later participants in this sport helped spread the myth that medieval armor was hard to\nmove in. For 10 points, name this sport in which knights on horseback attempt to unseat one\nanother, typically with a lance.",
      "answer": [
        "jousting",
        "joust",
        "tilting",
        "tilt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man delivered a speech that calls for “scorching irony,” in which the answer to the title\nquestion is “a day that reveals gross injustice and cruelty.” This author of “What to The Slave is\nThe Fourth of July?” lived at Cedar Hill and clashed with William Lloyd Garrison. This man fled\nTalbot County and wrote an autobiographical work describing learning to read in the sand. For\n10 points, name this author of My Bondage and My Freedom, a famous escaped slave and\nabolitionist.",
      "answer": [
        "Frederick Douglass",
        "Douglass",
        "Frederick Augustus Washington Bailey",
        "Bailey"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A conflict in this country was depicted in the 2006 novel Half of a Yellow Sun. A child soldier\nnamed Mene [meh-nay] appears in a novel from this country written in \"Rotten English\" by an\nactivist who criticized Royal Dutch Shell and was executed as a member of the \"Ogoni Nine.\" A\nonce-great wrestler in a novel from this country hangs himself after killing Ikemefuna [ick-aymuh-FOO-nuh] and beating his wife during the Week of Peace. For 10 points, name this home of\nthe Igbo author of Things Fall Apart, Chinua Achebe [CHIN-ooh-uh AH-chay-bay].",
      "answer": [
        "Federal Republic of Nigeria",
        "Nigeria"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A letter written by this man praises Walter Pater's Marius the Epicurean and asserts,\"Christ's\nplace indeed is with the poets.\" This man was imprisoned after suing the Marquess of\nQueensberry for libel, after which he wrote \"The Ballad of Reading Gaol [jail].\" In his most\nfamous play, a character discovered in a handbag in a Victoria Station attempts to win the hand\nof Gwendolen Fairfax. For 10 points, name this author of The Importance of Being Earnest and\nThe Picture of Dorian Gray.",
      "answer": [
        "Oscar Wilde",
        "Wilde",
        "Oscar Fingal O'Flahertie Wills Wilde"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A book by this thinker includes the chapter \"Formal Sex Relations\" as well as a close analysis of the kava ceremony. In one book, this thinker described the taupou system, which required women to keep their virginity. Derek Freeman attacked the work of this student of Franz Boas in a book titled for her \"Fateful Hoaxing.\" Much of her research was conducted on the island of Ta'u in the Pacific Ocean. For 10 points, name this anthropologist who wrote Coming of Age in Samoa.",
      "answer": "Margaret Mead"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote the cantata Gloria e Imeneo for Louis XV’s wedding and celebrated the defense of Corfu with the oratorio Juditha triumphans. Violas depict a barking sheepdog in one of his concertos, which was originally published with explanatory sonnets in The Contest Between Harmony and Invention. This violinst composed many of his works for a girl’s orphanage in Venice and was known as the “Red Priest.” for ten points, name this Baroque composer who depicted Spring in his Four Seasons.",
      "answer": "Antonio Vivaldi"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author is the title character of a J.M. Coetzee novel that centers on his excised chapter “At Tikhon’s.”Adreamaboutamanwhobeatsasicklyhorsetroublestheprotagonistofoneofhisnovels, who later encounters a man who commits suicide after saying that he is “going to America.” That protagonist by this author murders the pawnbroker Alyona Ivanovna, and eventually rediscovers Christianity with Sonya’s help. For ten points, name this creator of Rodion Raskolnikov, the author of Demons and Crime and Punishment.",
      "answer": "Fyodor Dostoyevsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a novel, Nicholas Branch is tasked with assembling information about this event, discovering the crippling dyslexia of the perpetrator. Permutations of this event are overseen by the Yellow Card Man in a 2011 Stephen King novel titled for the date of this event. This event, the subject of Libra and 11/22/63, was carried out from a school book depository in Dallas. For ten points, name this Presidential murder carried out by Lee Harvey Oswald.",
      "answer": "assassination of John Fitzgerald Kennedy or assassination of JFK"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author of Postcards from the Edge wrote multiple autobiographical works that openly discuss her positive experience with electroconvulsive therapy as treatment for bipolar disorder. This author of the memoir The Princess Diarist is, with her mother, the subject of Bright Lights, a documentary that premiered on HBO in January 2017, just weeks after their deaths. For ten points, name this mental health advocate, daughter of Debbie Reynolds, and actress who portrayed Princess Leia in the Star Wars films.",
      "answer": "Carrie Fisher"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man resisted his initial calling, saying that he was too young to speak; when he did begin his ministry, the people of his hometown tried to kill him, for which God promised destruction on the town of Anathoth. Near the end of his life, this man was forcibly taken to Egypt with his scribe Baruch, who recorded this man’s sayings into a namesake book. For ten points, name this Israelite, often called the “weeping prophet,” the author of the Book of Lamentations.",
      "answer": "Jeremiah"
    },
    {
      "question": "A three-part collection by this author depicts conditions in a besieged city in December, May, and August. The second part of an epilogue to a novel by this author attacks the Great Man theory of history, arguing that the importance of heroic figures like Napoleon is overrated. This author of Sevastopol Sketches wrote a novel about Pierre Bezuhkov set during the French invasion of Russia. For ten points, name this author of War and Peace.",
      "answer": "Leo Nikolayevich Tolstoy"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fourth and final section of a book by this man incorrectly tries to explain the origins of Earth’s tides. This man supported one of his arguments by citing the phases of Venus and apparent motion of sunspots. This man introduced the idea of inertial reference frames with a thought experiment about a man below deck on a ship, and wrote a book consisting of conversations between the laymen Sagredo, Simplicio, and Salviati. For ten points, name this author of a Diologue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems, who was charged with heresy for supporting heliocentrism.",
      "answer": [
        "Galileo Galilei",
        "either underlined name"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A thinker from this philosophical movement thought that “What’s a mistake but a kind of take?” was one of the secrets of the universe after inhaling too much nitrous oxide. The author of Making It Explicit, Robert Brandom, is considered a revivalist of this philosophical school with his teacher, Richard Rorty. A book titled for this philosophical school is subtitled “A New Name for Some Old Ways of Thinking.” For ten points, name this American philosophical movement that included C.S. Peirce [PURSE], John Dewey, and William James.",
      "answer": "pragmatism"
    },
    {
      "question": "This poem, which was written on a trip to visit the father of the author’s lover Chester Kallman, was read on NPR following the 9/11 attacks. The “Daisy” Ad uses a variation of the final line from this poem, which states “We must love each other, or we must die.” This poem’s author claims he was “in one of the dives / On Fifty-second Street” when he heard the news of Germany invading Poland. For ten points, name this W.H. Auden poem written at, and named for, the start of World War II.",
      "answer": "September 1, 1939"
    },
    {
      "question": "This owner of the Poplar Hall plantation wrote that the “difficulty of establishing particular manufactures [...] is almost insuperable” in the second entry of a series that this man published under the name “A Farmer.” This man’s most famous work was addressed to a king who refused to read it, instead proclaiming that the colonists had “proceeded to open and avowed rebellion.” For ten points, name this “Penman of the Revolution,” a founding father from Pennsylvania who drafted the Olive Branch Petition.",
      "answer": "John Dickinson"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a work by this man, the line “either I’m nobody, or I’m a nation” is spoken by Shabine, who later comments on the Middle Passage. This man lamented about the bad deeds of “Hawkins, Walter Raleigh, [and] Drake” in another work, which notes that the “smell of dead limes” signifies the “leprosy of empire.” This poet described the sinking of the Marlborough in a work in which Achille loves Major Dennis Plunkett’s servant, Helen. For ten points, name this Saint Lucian poet who wrote the Iliad-inspired “Omeros.”",
      "answer": "Derek Walcott"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thismandescribedandnamesatypeofbeautycontestwherethejudgesratebasedonhowtheythink other people will rate. This man, who proposed that it may be economically productive to pay people to bury and dig up money, famously criticized the punitive measures found in the Treaty of Versailles in his book The Economic Consequences of the Peace. For ten points, name this author of The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money, an early 20th century British economist.",
      "answer": "John Maynard Keynes"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once offered 500 pounds for the purchase of the twelve-year-old girl Teresa Makri, a failed bid that led to his poem “Maid of Athens, ere we part.” After meeting his cousin at a ball, he compared her to “the night of cloudless climes and starry skies” in another poem. This man, who described the travels of a disillusioned man in Childe Harold’s Pilgrimage, died in Missolonghi in 1824. “She Walks in Beauty” and Don Juan [JOO-un] were written by, for ten points, what English poet who died fighting in the Greek War of Independence?",
      "answer": "Lord George Gordon Byron"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author described his annoyance with police calling him “Joe” in his autobiographical memoir Joseph Anton, named for his pseudonym. A novel by this author depicts Muhammad’s early followers alongside stories about Jibreel Farishta and Saladin Chamcha. 2019’s Quichotte was written by, for ten points, what British-Indian novelist who became the subject of a fatwa from Ayatollah Khomeini for his novel The Satanic Verses?",
      "answer": "Salman Rushdie"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a result of a dispute with Peter Ludvig Moller, this thinker was harassed on the streets of his hometown in what became known as the Corsair Affair. In one book, this thinker claimed that only by “virtue of the absurd” were movements of faith possible. This thinker used the teleological suspension of the ethical to justify Abraham’s sacrifice of Isaac. For ten points, name this Danish thinker who discussed the “leap of faith” and wrote Fear and Trembling.",
      "answer": "Soren Kierkegaard"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a novel written in this language, an old man collects banned books obtained while working as a paper crusher. In another novel written in this language, a professor is robbed after protesting in Thailand and a female dog named after a Tolstoy novel is given as a gift to Tereza. After writing The Garden Party, an author in this language co-founded Charter 77 and gained political power in the Velvet Revolution. For ten points, name this language used by Bohumil Hrabal, Milan Kundera, and Vaclav Havel.",
      "answer": "Czech"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ferdinand Lot questioned whether this man actually defeated 430 thousand enemy soldiers, though Ernest Desjardins [[day-zhar-DAH]] credited that number to a transcription error. Aulus Hirtius [[OW-luss HEAR-shus]] wrote the eighth book of one of this man's works which features Vorenus and Pullo. A work by this man describes his defeat of Vercingetorix [[VEHR-sin-GET-or-rix]], and this man wrote Commentaries on the Gallic Wars. Known for crossing the Rubicon, for ten points, who was this Roman who was killed on the Ides of March?",
      "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Herman Melville's novel The Confidence-Man depicts travelers telling stories along this body of water. In one novel, a pair of con artists traveling on this body of water pretend to be King Louis XVII and the Duke of Nonesuch [[NUN-such]]. A memoir titled Life on [this body of water] was written by Mark Twain, who set many of his novels along this waterway. For ten points, name this long U.S. river, on which Jim and Huckleberry Finn float in a raft.",
      "answer": "Mississippi River 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was born in what is today Algeria and wrote one of the first autobiographies in Western literature in which he relates his sinful early life and the tireless efforts of his mother, Monica, to save his soul. As a young man in Carthage, this future theologian was enamored of Manichaeism [[man-ih-KEE-ism]], the belief in an eternal conflict between light and darkness. In Milan, this man met Saint Ambrose, who eventually baptized him into the Catholic church. For ten points, what saint and Bishop of Hippo wrote the Confessions?",
      "answer": "Saint Augustine of Hippo 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "After being forced to flee his home, this thinker remarked, \"What progress we are making. In the Middle Ages they would have burned me. Now, they are content with burning my books.\" This thinker claimed that Judaism was influenced by Akhenaten in Moses and Monotheism. This thinker divided the subconscious into the ego, superego, and the id. This thinker, the author of The Interpretation of Dreams, formulated the Oedipal Complex. For ten points, name this Austrian psychologist, the father of psychoanalysis.",
      "answer": "Sigmund Freud"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author's alleged incestuous relationship with his half-sister may have resulted in the birth of Elizabeth Medora Leigh. This author's only legitimate child was the early computer scientist Ada Lovelace. This author was described as \"mad, bad, and dangerous to know\" by his mistress Lady Caroline Lamb. This author died of sepsis before he could help attack the Ottoman fortress of Lepanto during the Greek War for Independence. For ten points, name this Romantic poet, the author of \"She Walks in Beauty.\"",
      "answer": "Lord Byron or George Gordon"
    },
    {
      "question": "A crossbowmen who may have practiced this discipline shot and killed Richard the Lionheart during a siege of Chalus in France. Caelius Apicius [[ah-PIH-kee-us]] wrote a work in this field in Vulgar Latin which opens with the chapter Epimeles, or \"The Careful Housekeeper.\" Gervase Markham wrote a work in this discipline named The English Housewife, including a chapter titled \"Banqueting Stuff.\" De re culinaria is a pamphlet on, for ten points, what discipline which involves preparing food?",
      "answer": [
        "Cooking",
        "Gastronomy",
        "Culinary arts before \"culinaria\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a work in this language, the eardstapa, or \"Wanderer,\" is in self-imposed exile after losing his lord and fellow retainers during a raid. The long form poem The Age of Anxiety by W.H. Auden is in this specific language, emulating an early style of alliterative verse. The limbs of a monster named Grendel are taken off in a mead hall by the title hero of an epic poem in this language. The poem Beowulf is written in, for ten points, which medieval language of the British isles influenced by Old Norse?",
      "answer": "Old English"
    },
    {
      "question": "In \"The Contagiousness of Puerperal Fever,\" this man correctly concluded that physicians not washing their hands was causing postpartum infections in their pregnant patients. While corresponding with William T. G. Morton, this American coined the term \"anesthesia.\" A poem by this man describes a vessel \"once red with heroes' blood,\" and contributed to the decision not to decommission the USS Constitution. The poem \"Old Ironsides\" was written by, for ten points, which fireside poet?",
      "answer": "Oliver Wendell Holmes Sr."
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This play included a scene in which a character is told “Thou shalt get kings” to please its\nauthor’s patron, James I. The heir Donalbain [DONN-ull-bane] goes into hiding during this play,\nwhose title character is killed after Birnam Wood is brought to Dunsinane [DUNN-sinn-ane].\nThe three Weird Sisters appear in, for 10 points, what Shakespeare play, which culminates with\nMacduff slaying the title Scottish king?",
        "answer": [
          "The Tragedy of Macbeth",
          "Macbeth"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the “Tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow” soliloquy, Macbeth claims that “life’s\nbut a walking” one of what thing?",
        "answer": "shadow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one book, this man proposed that Moses was a relative of the Egyptian Akhenaten. This\nman investigated views of incest among the Aborigines in the first section of his book Totem and\nTaboo. This man conceived of the \"death drive\" in a book attributing human behavior to sexual\ndrive. For 10 points, name this psychologist who conceived of the Oedipus complex and founded\npsychoanalysis.",
        "answer": [
          "Sigmund Freud",
          "Freud",
          "Sigismund Schlomo Freud"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Freud’s daughter Anna authored a book titled for the “Ego” and what concepts, whose\nexamples include regression and projection?",
        "answer": "defense mechanisms"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person, who was hired after her critical response to the “Quiet Observer” column in the\nPittsburgh Dispatch won admirers, once spent 10 days undercover at Blackwell’s Island in order\nto expose the cruel treatment of the mentally ill. She took her pen name from a Stephen Foster\nsong and her most well-known feat involved traveling by burro, train and ship. For 10 points,\nname this “stunt reporter” who completed a 72-day round-the-world trip in 1889.",
        "answer": [
          "Nellie Bly",
          "Bly",
          "Elizabeth Jane Cochran",
          "Cochran"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nellie Bly's journey thus beat the pace set by this author's protagonist Phileas Fogg in the\nnovel Around the World in 80 Days.",
        "answer": [
          "Jules Verne",
          "Verne",
          "Jules Gabriel Verne"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author wrote of a colonel serving Queen Anne in The History of Henry Esmond and of an\nIrishman who fights in the Seven Years’ War and the American Revolution in The Luck of Barry\nLyndon. Another of his novels opens at Miss Pinkerton’s Academy and contrasts the\nmanipulative Becky Sharp with the naïve Amelia Sedley. For 10 points, name this Victorian\nauthor of Vanity Fair.",
        "answer": [
          "William Makepeace Thackeray",
          "Thackeray",
          "William Thackeray"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Waterloo figures prominently in both Vanity Fair and The Charterhouse\nof Parma, a novel by what French author?",
        "answer": [
          "Stendhal",
          "Marie-Henri Beyle",
          "Beyle"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Zappo Zaps were used to collect taxes in this modern-day nation. Mark Twain wrote a satirical “soliloquy” skewering the ruler of a colony in this modern-day nation. The Casement Report detailed terrible abuse of natives forced to harvest rubber in this nation, which inspired Heart of Darkness. For 10 points, name this modern nation, which was originally the personal African colony of King Leopold II of Belgium.",
        "answer": "Democratic Republic of the Congo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Leopold used this British explorer, who fought on both sides in the US Civil War, to explore and claim the Congo. He is better-known for finding Dr. Livingstone.",
        "answer": "Henry Morton Stanley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of this event, its subject wrote that he was “now quite certain that the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away.” During this event, Matthew Ruppert survived being shot in the face during Israel Greene’s attack on the engine house where hostages were being held. Robert E. Lee’s marines ended this event, which sought to capture weapons in preparation for a slave revolt. For ten points, name this October 1859 event in which a federal arsenal was briefly seized by John Brown.",
        "answer": "Raid on Harpers Ferry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brown requested this abolitionist’s help with the raid, but this author of My Bondage and My Freedom and a Narrative of his life as a slave declined.",
        "answer": "Frederick Douglass"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author wrote a work subtitled “The Long Parliament” about the English Civil War. Another work by this author states that “dark and erroneous doctrines” are used by a “confederacy of deceivers” to help create a “Kingdom of Darkness.” That work by this author states that there only exist three types of commonwealth, of which absolute monarchy is the best option. For ten points, name this author who described life as “nasty, brutish, and short” in Leviathan.",
        "answer": "Thomas Hobbes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Hobbes’ Leviathan is one of the earliest works that discusses this concept. This concept, which describes how individuals must sacrifice individual rights to their rulers, also titles a work by Jean Jacques Rousseau.",
        "answer": "social contract"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This writer described meeting Arthur Koestler in the autobiography I Wonder As I Wander, and said “there’s never been equality for me” in “Let America Be America Again.” In one poem, this man observed a singer “droning a drowsy syncopated tune,” while in another he “heard the singing of the Mississippi when Abe Lincoln went down to New Orleans”. For ten points, name this Harlem Renaissance poet of “The Weary Blues” and “The Negro Speaks of Rivers.”",
        "answer": "Langston Hughes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Lorraine Hansberry play about the Younger family’s struggle with housing discrimination takes its title from this Hughes poem.",
        "answer": "Harlem or A Dream Deferred"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, a comparison to David and Jonathan was used to answer the question “What is the ‘love that dare not speak its name?’” This event was triggered by the Marquess of Queensbury’s victory in a libel suit. In its aftermath, its subject wrote a 50,000 word letter to “Bosie” while serving a sentence of hard labor at Reading Gaol [redding jail]. For ten points, name this 1895 event in which the author of The Picture of Dorian Gray and The Importance of Being Earnest was convicted of inappropriate relations with Lord Alfred Douglas.",
        "answer": [
          "the trial of Oscar Wilde for homosexuality or Regina v. Wilde",
          "descriptions of Oscar Wilde being arrested and/or charged for homosexual behavior, gross indecency and/or sodomy",
          "imprisonment of Oscar Wilde"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wilde’s 50,000 word letter was given this title, from the Latin for “from the depths.”",
        "answer": "De Profundis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This writer’s opposition to the collection of indemnities by William Ament after the Boxer Rebellion prompted him to write an essay “To the Person Sitting in Darkness.” This author made a chronicle of a westward stagecoach journey with his brother Orion. This author of Roughing It also wrote about his early years as an apprentice to a steamboat captain in Life on the Mississippi, in which he explained the genesis of his pen name. For ten points, name this author, born Samuel Langhorne Clemens, famous for his Adventures of Tom Sawyer.",
        "answer": [
          "Mark Twain",
          "Samuel Langhorne Clemens before read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "An 1873 book by Mark Twain and Charley Dudley Warner lends its title to what time period in American history between 1870 and 1900, in which post-Civil War opulence hid the unsavory nature of urban poverty?",
        "answer": [
          "the Gilded Age",
          "Gilded Age: A Tale of Today"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character says “It is always better / to avenge dear ones than to indulge in mourning” to a grieving friend after the death of a man whose name translates as “ash army.” This character once lost a week-long swimming contest to his friend Breca. This man, who dies in combat with a dragon, is the subject of a poem that was translated by Seamus Heaney. For ten points, name this hero who kills Grendel and Grendel’s mother in an Old English epic poem.",
        "answer": "Beowulf"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author claimed that the value of Beowulf as poetry, rather than as a historical document, had been overlooked in the English literary tradition in his lecture Beowulf: The Monsters and the Critics.",
        "answer": "J.R.R. Tolkien or John Ronald Reuen Tolkien"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the sixth edition of this work, its author added a new chapter to respond to the criticisms of George Jackson Mivart. Its author was motivated to publish following Alfred Russell Wallace’s paper containing similar ideas. This work doesn’t analyze the human race, which was later tackled by its author’s The Descent of Man. For ten points, name this book that introduced evolution by natural selection, the magnum opus of Charles Darwin.",
        "answer": "On the Origin of Species"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Advocates for Darwin’s work included this man, his “Bulldog,” who debated Samuel Wilberforce at Oxford in 1860. This man’s grandsons included Julian, an accomplished biologist in his own right.",
        "answer": "Thomas Henry Huxley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer dedicated his song “The Little Brook” to Joseph Goebbels and wrote an Olympic Hymn that premiered at the 1936 Berlin Olympics. This composer used both a D clarinet and the French horn to represent the title trickster in his tone poem Till Eulenspeigel’s Merry Pranks. A C-G-C motif opens the “Sunrise” section of another tone poem by this composer, based on a book by Friedrich Nietzsche [nee-cha]. For ten points, name this composer of Also Sprach Zarathustra.",
        "answer": "Richard Strauss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Richard Strauss also wrote this opera, based on an Oscar Wilde play, in which the title daughter of Herod performs the “Dance of the Seven Veils.”",
        "answer": "Salome"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s forces blundered by shooting Hayward Shepherd in the view of train passengers, who then alerted authorities. An earlier group led by this man attempted to kill Dutch Henry in the Pottawatomie Massacre during Bleeding Kansas. The Battle Hymn of the Republic was set to the tune of a song about the body of this man, who was hanged for attacking a federal armory. For ten points, name this radical abolitionist who launched an 1859 raid on Harpers Ferry.",
        "answer": "John Brown"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle Hymn of the Republic was written by this poet and activist, who was inspired by the melody of “John Brown’s Body.”",
        "answer": "Julia Ward Howe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man once threw his alcoholic friend John Collins into a river when he refused to row a boat. This man founded an intellectual group known as either the Leather Apron Society or the Junto [jun-toh]. In Boston, this man used the pseudonym Silence Dogood to send letters to The New-England Courant; after he moved to Philadelphia, he switched newspapers to work on The Pennsylvania Gazette. For ten points, name this founding father who wrote and published Poor Richard’s Almanack.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1754, Franklin’s Pennsylvania Gazette published this political cartoon advocating for colonial unity. This cartoon identifies eight regions, including New England but not Georgia, as segments of a cut snake.",
        "answer": [
          "Join,",
          "Die"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A character created by this author is nicknamed “We don’t do that” after he is punished for refusing to carry a rifle in a parade. This author devoted one chapter to each of 100 years in his book My Century. This author, who admitted to being a member of the Waffen-SS in his memoir Peeling the Onion, wrote a novel in which Oskar Matzerath refuses to grow past the age of three. For ten points, name this German author of The Tin Drum.",
        "answer": "Gunter Grass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Grass’s The Tin Drum, Cat and Mouse, and Dog Years form a trilogy named after this Polish city that existed as an independent city-state between 1920 and 1939.",
        "answer": [
          "Danzig Trilogy",
          "Gdansk"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This Chief Justice wrote that the power to determine whether a state government was a “legitimate republican” one was a political question in Luther v. Borden. This Chief Justice at the time of the Amistad case also wrote a controversial opinion denying the plaintiff standing on account of his race and ruling the Missouri Compromise unconstitutional. The Dred Scott v. Sanford case was decided by, for ten points, what Chief Justice who presided from 1836 to 1864?",
        "answer": "Roger Taney , but be lenient"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Contract Clause case during Taney’s tenure concerned charters granted to construct these structures; that case was named after the “Charles River” and “Warren” examples of these structures.",
        "answer": [
          "bridges",
          "Charles River Bridge v. Warren Bridge"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Thisthinkerarguedthattotemicreligionsplayedalargepartindevelopingthecollectiveconsciousness of a people in his Rules of the Sociological Method. In one study, this man pointed to stronger Catholic social controls as diminishing a phenomenon that he divided into egoistic, altruistic, fatalistic, and anomic types. Auguste Comte inspired, for ten points, what author of Elementary Forms of Religious Life and Suicide, a French pioneer of sociology?",
        "answer": "Emile Durkheim"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In his first published work, Durkheim stated that this phenomenon in Society necessitated the development of “organic solidarity” over “mechanical solidarity.”",
        "answer": "the Division of Labor in Society"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThismandiedinhissleepathissummerhomeinFlorida,TheCasements.InadepictionbyPuck,this man’s company was shown as an octopus grabbing lawmakers and reaching for the White House. Despite his son having ordered the action, this man was criticized for the deadly force brought against protesting coal miners at his Ludlow mine. This man’s corrupt business practices were exposed by muckraker Ida Tarbell, who wrote a history of his company. For ten points, name this richest ever American, the founder of Standard Oil.",
        "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ida Tarbell’s expose of Rockefeller’s practices was published by this magazine, which was edited by Lincoln Steffens.",
        "answer": "McClure’s Magazine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The subject of this poem is “loosed from its dream of life” “six miles from earth.” The author of this poem later noted that its subject would have been a “short small man” who “looked like the fetus in the womb,” “hunched upside-down in his little sphere.” This five line poem about the helplessness of war jarringly ends “When I died they washed me out [...] with a hose.” For ten points, name this World War II poem whose subject operated machine guns under a B-24 bomber until his death.",
        "answer": "The Death of the Ball Turret Gunner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This American poet and tower operator in the Air Force wrote “The Death of the Ball Turret Gunner.”",
        "answer": "Randall Jarrell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author’s essay “Blind Nightmare” and book Underground each discuss a terrorist attack on a subway system carried out by the Aum Shinrikyo doomsday cult. That attack also influenced a novel by this author that depicts Aomame and Tengo falling into an alternative version of the year 1984. Hong Kong censored Killing Commendatore, the most recent novel by, for ten points, what Japanese novelist of 1Q84 and The Wind Up Bird Chronicle?",
        "answer": "Haruki Murakami"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Murakami collection including “Honey Pie” and “Super-Frog Saves Tokyo” was inspired by one of these events that killed over 4,000 people in Kobe in 1995.",
        "answer": [
          "earthquake",
          "the Kobe earthquake",
          "Great Hanshin Earthquake",
          "after the quake"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman asked a series of 42 questions about scripture in a letter she likely wrote from the Oratory of the Paraclete. A man named Fulbert was convinced that this woman could be tutored by a man who lusted after her; shortly thereafter, this woman gave birth to a son named Astrolabe, and Fulbert led a mob that castrated her tutor. Marriage and prostitution are compared in the writings of, for ten points, what 12th century French feminist writer who is most famous for her correspondences with the author of Sic et Non, Pierre Ab´elard?",
        "answer": "H´eloise d’Argenteuil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The story of H´eloise inspired this immensely popular 1761 French epistolary novel. Its title character, described as “the new H´eloise,” is tutored by Saint Preux and marries Wolmar, a character based on the author’s patron, Baron d’Holbach.",
        "answer": [
          "Julie,",
          "the New Heloise"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Abram Joseph Ryan was considered the \"Poet-Priest\" of one side of this war for poems like \"The Conquered Banner.\" Allen Tate wrote a modernist poem as an “Ode” to this war’s dead, told by a narrator in a graveyard on an \"Ambitious November.” Ambrose Bierce’s experiences during this war inspired his short story “Chickamauga.” Jim Conklin dies from blood loss in an engagement in this war, causing Henry Fleming to flee the battlefield. For ten points, name this war depicted in The Red Badge of Courage.",
        "answer": "American Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“Ode to the Confederate Dead” inspired this poet to write \"For the Union Dead,\" which is set in Boston Common. He also wrote \"The Quaker Graveyard in Nantucket.\"",
        "answer": "Robert Lowell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One author wrote during one of these events, \"I have never lived so merrily.\" One of these events, which may have been ended by a fire, was written about in the diary of Samuel Pepys [[PEEPS]]. Another of these events named for Justinian supposedly began in Pelesium and traveled by grain ship to Constantinople. A 14th century iteration of these events was likely begun by Genoese traders and killed half of Europe’s population. For ten points, name these “plagues” caused by flea infested rats.",
        "answer": [
          "Outbreaks of Bubonic Plague",
          "Plague before mentioned",
          "The Black Death",
          "Great Plague of London before \"plague\"",
          "Plague of Justinian before \"plague\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Samuel Pepys’s diary begins with the restoration of this dynasty’s King Charles II, much to Pepys’s unhappiness as he was a supporter of Oliver Cromwell.",
        "answer": [
          "Stuart Dynasty or Stuarts",
          "or House of Stuart 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 4"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person, who got himself intentionally court martialed out of West Point, published a book of poetry with works like “Tamerlane” after a generous donation from his fellow cadets. The 1841 killing of the “Beautiful Cigar Girl” inspired this man's novel \"The Mystery of Marie Rogêt\" [[ROH-ZHEH]] featuring detective C. Auguste Dupin. The tearing down of the historic but derelict Hezekiah House in Boston inspired this writer’s story “The Fall of the House of Usher.” For ten points, name this American author of “The Pit and the Pendulum” and “The Raven.”",
        "answer": "Edgar Allan Poe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "By claiming to be a Whig, Edgar Allan Poe attempted to get a clerical post in this president's bureaucracy but was too drunk to show up to that 1841 meeting.",
        "answer": "John Tyler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Prince Albert loaned his horses to model for a statue of this woman and her daughters now situated on Westminster Bridge. This woman's husband, Prasutagus [[prah- soo-TAY-gus]], willed half of his kingdom to his daughters and half to the emperor. The Roman Empire's gross mistreatment of this woman and her family led her to rebel against Governor Gaius Suetonius Paulinus and lead a tribal army across Britain to burn the city of Londinium. For ten points, name this woman, a modern folk hero and the historical queen of the Celtic Iceni [[eye-SEEN-ee]].",
        "answer": [
          "Boudica or Boadicea",
          "or Boudicea",
          "or Buddug"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Poet Laureate during the reign of Queen Victoria wrote a poem titled \"Boadicea\" as well as a tale of King Arthur titled Idylls of the King.",
        "answer": "Alfred, Lord Tennyson 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A novel by this author centers on the intersex Laurence and is titled The Hermaphrodite. This author published the Mother's Day Proclamation as an \"Appeal to womanhood\" following the Civil War. Inspired by a William Steffe song, this person wrote a work which features the chorus \"Glory! Glory! Hallelujah!\" which was written after hearing some soldiers sing \"John Brown's Body.\" For ten points, name this woman who married the founder of the Perkins School for the Blind and composed the \"Battle Hymn of the Republic.\"",
        "answer": "Julia Ward Howe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The \"Battle Hymn of the Republic\" was a show-stopper at concerts held by this man, whose eighteen number-one hits in the U.S. included \"Heartbreak Hotel\" and \"Suspicious Minds.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Elvis Presley",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A biography accused this author of plagiarizing Emma Langdon Roche in a 1928 article recapping an interview with slave trade survivor Cudjoe Lewis. This author depicted the Southern practice of \"paramour rights\" in her 1934 novel Jonah's Gourd Vine. This author extensively collected Caribbean and southern folklore in books such as Tell My Horse and Mules and Men. For ten points, name this author of a 1937 novel about the Black town of Eatonville, Florida, Their Eyes Were Watching God.",
        "answer": "Zora Neale Hurston"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hurston's 1948 novel about Jim Meserve's pursuit of Arvay Henson is titled for a Seraph on what river, which also appears in the first line of the Florida state song, \"Old Folks at Home\"? Arising in the Okefenokee Swamp, it hosted many Timucua settlements.",
        "answer": "Suwanee River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This attorney charged that Reuben Crandall's publications instigated slaves to rebel in the leadup to the Snow Riot. This man served as a defense lawyer for Sam Houston after he caned William Stanbery. This man was detained aboard the HMS Tonnant to negotiate the release of William Beanes, during which time he wrote a poem that mentions \"the shore dimly seen through the mists of the deep.\" For ten points, name this lawyer, who wrote a poem about the shelling of Fort McHenry that would later become \"The Star-Spangled Banner.\"",
        "answer": "Francis Scott Key"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Key led which \"Society\" which facilitated the passage of Free Black people to settlements predominantly in West Africa?",
        "answer": "American Colonization Society"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author described his time living in Vermont in the memoir The Grain Between the Millstones. Another book by this man discusses events such as the Kengir Uprising and the process of segregating zeks. This frequent subject of the samizdat circulation process depicted the director Caesar and the Baptist Alyosha in a novel based on his own time as an Article 58 violator arrested by SMERSH. For ten points, name this Soviet author of The Gulag Archipelago and One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovitch.",
        "answer": "Aleksandr Isayevich Solzhenitsyn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1968 Solzhenitsyn novel is titled for a facility that treats this disease, which protagonist Oleg Kostoglotov analogizes to Stalinism.",
        "answer": [
          "Cancer",
          "Cancer Ward"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Berber People",
      "prompt": "Concerning the history of the Berbers, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Catholic Church father of Berber origin who wrote Confessions and City of God.",
          "answer": "St. Augustine of Hippo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phoenician city-state in North Africa which used Berber horsemen as mercenaries.",
          "answer": [
            "Carthage",
            "Carthago"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Arab caliphate that succeeded the Rashidun and conquered the Berbers in the 8th century.",
          "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Berber scholar of the 14th century who departed from Morocco for the hajj and became the most traveled explorer in history prior to the Industrial Revolution.",
          "answer": "Ibn Battuta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Berber kingdom and rival of Rome led by Kings Jugurtha and Massinissa.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Numidia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medieval Berber caliphate that overthrew the Almoravids and controlled both the Maghreb and Andalusia.",
          "answer": "Almohad Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern Saharan nation which shares its name with a Berber kingdom that served as a client state to Rome.",
          "answer": "Mauretania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Berber writer of The Golden Ass, the only novel to survive in its entirety from the Roman period.",
          "answer": "Apuleius or Lucius Apuleius Madaurensis"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a novel by this author, Edgar, the Master of Ravenswood, dies in quicksand after\nLucy stabs Bucklaw in a bridal chamber. This author of The Bride of Lammermoor wrote a\nnovel in which (20 pts) ",
        "El Desdichado [dess-dee-cod-oh] jousts with Maurice de Bracy and other\nknights. Frank Osbaldistone narrates this author’s novel (10 pts) ",
        "Rob Roy, which is part of his\nWaverley series. Cedric the Saxon’s son, Wilfrid, is the title character of this author’s novel set\nin 12th-century England. For 10 points, name this British author of historical romances such as\nIvanhoe."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sir Walter Scott",
        "Scott",
        "Walter Scott"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A chapter of this book describes the \"inexhaustible entertainment\" of its author's surroundings while hoeing his bean field. A poem by Thomas Carew ends a chapter of this book that includes a meticulous list of its author's (20 pts)",
        "expenditures. This book's author proposes the \"realometer\" in its chapter \"Where I (10 pts)",
        "Lived, and What I Lived For.\" The author of this book stressed \"economy\" and \"self-sufficiency\" while living on the land of his friend Ralph Waldo Emerson. For 10 points, name this memoir written by the transcendentalist Henry David Thoreau."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Walden",
        "or, Life in the Woods"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A photograph from this book depicts three young boys sleeping on a barrel, and it derives its title from a line in Rabelais’ Gargantua and Pantagruel. The then-recent invention of flash photography allowed this book’s creator to capture the (20 pts)",
        "poorly-lit places documented in this book, and its last chapter claims that New York’s “tremendous, ever swelling (10 pts)",
        "crowd of wage earners” is “not housed decently.” For 10 points, name this Jacob Riis book that exposed poor living conditions in urban tenements."
      ],
      "answer": "How the Other Half Lives"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author commented on Athenian inheritance laws in one play, in which Hypermnestra is unable to kill her husband after being instructed to do so. This author of the Danaid used Susa as the setting of a play about Xerxes’s defeat at Salamis. He wrote about (20 pts)",
        "Clytemnestra’s killing of her husband and the ensuing revenge of Orestes in a prize-winning trilogy, and two of Oedipus’s sons fight in this author’s (10 pts)",
        "Seven Against Thebes. For ten points, name this ancient Greek tragedian, the author of The Persians and the Oresteia trilogy."
      ],
      "answer": "Aeschylus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work concludes by recommending “an increasing sense that a thing won by breaking the rules of the game is not worth the winning.” It notes how “the speculative character of the business would be done away with” if its subject was able to control the (20 pts)",
        "shipping and refining aspects of production. This work grew out of interviews with Henry Rogers, and was followed by a two-part profile of its subject’s CEO. (10 pts)",
        "McClure’s magazine published a serialized version of, for ten points, what 1904 muckraking expos´e by Ida Tarbell into the inner workings of John D. Rockefeller’s company? ANSWER:TheHistoryof (the)StandardOilCompany(acceptanyanswerthatmentionstheHistory of Standard Oil, ignoring the usual “the title must be exact” rule, as it’s been published under many permutations; do not prompt on Standard Oil alone) (6) One performer of this instrument, who wrote “Nuages” and “Minor Swing,” collaborated with Stephane Grapelli and combined jazz with his native Romani music. A concerto for this instrument was inspired by the palace gardens of King Philip II in Aranjuez [air-an-weth] and was written by (+) Joaquin [wha-keen] Rodrigo. A performer of this instrument was inspired by the fight against Hitler to decorate his with the phrase “This Machine (*) Kills Fascists.” Django Reinhardt and the writer of “This Land Is Your Land,” Woody Guthrie, both played, for ten points, what instrument that has six strings and frets?"
      ],
      "answer": "guitar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This book was mostly financed by Wilhelm Wolff, who also was the dedicatee of the only volume of this work to be published during its author’s lifetime. A law describing the tendency of the rate of (20 pts)",
        "profit to fall was first described in this work’s Volume III, and it claims that class divisions came to be during a “primitive accumulation.” This work describes social relations and their transmutation into (10 pts)",
        "economic relations in its section on “commodity fetishism”. For ten points, name this analysis of the title economic concept, written by Karl Marx."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Das Kapital",
        "Capital"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Works from this dynasty describe Yang Guifei, one of the four beauties. During this dynasty, Emperor Xuangzong and Wang Wei resided in Chang’an before being displaced by rebels. “Departing from (20 pts)",
        "Baidi in the Morning” was written by one author from this dynasty while returning from exile after the An Lushan rebellion. (10 pts)",
        "“Drinking Alone by Moonlight” and “The River Merchant’s Wife” were written by Li Bai during, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty, known as the “golden age” of Chinese poetry, that followed the Sui dynasty?"
      ],
      "answer": "Tang Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one book by this author, the title peasant is adopted by Frederick Barbarossa and goes in search of the mythical Kingdom of Prester John. In another work of his, the Abbe della Piccola is the alter-ego of Simone Simonini, who is inspired by real-life individuals and forgeries to write The Protocols of the Elders of Zion. This author of (20 pts)",
        "Baudolino and The Prague Cemetery included a fictionalized version of Roger Bacon, (10 pts)",
        "William of Baskerville, in a historical novel about murders in a monastery. For ten points, name this Italian author of The Name of the Rose."
      ],
      "answer": "Umberto Eco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The protagonist of this novel duels an officer after he perceives an insult to his wife at the English Club, then later obsesses over killing an enemy monarch who is occupying a foreign capital. This novel depicts the obese, one-eyed General (20 pts)",
        "Kutuzov as a spiritual man who kneels in thanks before an icon. Princess H´el`ene dies near the end of this book, which contains lengthy descriptions of the (10 pts)",
        "Battles of Austerlitz and Borodino. For ten points, name this novel set during Napoleon’s invasion of Russia by Leo Tolstoy."
      ],
      "answer": "War and Peace or Voyna i mir"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Johannes Ockeghem wrote the first surviving polyphonic example of this composition. Berlioz wrote one of these pieces with four brass bands to commemorate the July Revolution. These pieces normally feature a (20 pts)",
        "hymn attributed to Thomas of Celano. Another of these pieces includes a trombone solo in its “Tuba Mirum” section and was completed by Franz (10 pts)",
        "Sussmayr after its composer died while working on its “Lacrimosa.” A “Dies Irae” is usually found in, for ten points, what type of composition that was Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart’s last, a mass for the dead?"
      ],
      "answer": "requiems or requiem mass"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this man’s citizen militia fled, the Spanish sacked the city of Prato in 1512, ending the rule of Piero Soderini. This man wrote that “because Fortune is a (20 pts)",
        "woman, one must thrash her to have one’s way with her,” and he discussed the first 10 books of the History of Rome in his Discourses on Livy. Another work by this author views Cesare Borgia as a model (10 pts)",
        "ruler, claims that it is better to be feared than to be loved. and was dedicated to Lorenzo d’Medici. For ten points, name this Italian author of The Prince."
      ],
      "answer": "Niccol´o Machiavelli"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As the leader of one governmental agency, this man claimed “whatever their politics, they shall be fed!” and refused to deny relief for the Soviet Union. This man and his wife would frequently converse in Mandarin to foil eavesdroppers, and this former (20 pts)",
        "engineer authored a widely read textbook on the Principles of Mining. This President reluctantly signed the Hawley-Smoot Tariff, (10 pts)",
        "worsening an economic disaster. For ten points, name this oft-maligned Republican President, the namesake of shantytowns during his time in office at the start of the Great Depression."
      ],
      "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A crime is committed on this holiday in the Hercule Poirot story “Murder in the Mews.” The namesake of this holiday is idolized as a distant ancestor of the central family of the novel Martin Chuzzlewit. (20 pts)",
        "Evey [ee-vee] Hammond is saved from assault on this holiday in a graphic novel by Alan Moore; a year later, she sets a subway train full of explosives to blow up a government building. The title character of (10 pts)",
        "V for Vendetta wears a mask representing the namesake of, for ten points, what British holiday, the subject of the rhyme “Remember, remember, the fifth of November?”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Guy Fawkes Day and/or Night",
        "the Fifth of November until read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a novel, this historical figure laments seeing Venus for the last time on December 17th after a voyage along the Magdalena River. This man’s personal papers were edited by Daniel O’Leary. This author of the Cartagena (20 pts)",
        "Manifesto is the subject of Gabriel Garcia Marquez’s novel The General in His Labyrinth; that book is set after he resigned the presidency of (10 pts)",
        "Gran Colombia in 1830. For ten points, name this South American independence leader, nicknamed “The Liberator.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Simon Bolivar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An essay by Simone Weil claims that the central theme of a poem by this author is unbridled force and power. According to a tradition known as the Certamen, Hesiod won a bronze tripod in a (20 pts)",
        "poetry contest against this man. Richmond Lattimore is best known for his translations of this man’s works, one of which begins by describing the rage of (10 pts)",
        "Achilles when his concubine is seized by Agamemnon. For ten points, name this blind Greek poet who wrote about the Trojan War in the Iliad."
      ],
      "answer": "Homer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author wrote about a young couple who commit suicide after the failure of an uprising in late February in his story “Patriotism.” This author’s death (20 pts)",
        "poem, which declares that “failing is the essence of a flower,” was composed in preparation for his takeover of an army outpost. (10 pts)",
        "The Temple of the Golden Pavilion was written by, for ten points, what Japanese author who completed his The Sea of Fertility series before his ritual suicide, or seppuku, after the failure of an imperialist coup in 1970?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yukio Mishima or Kimitake Hiraoka",
        "names in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s writings detail Eadburh’s [ed-buh’s] accidental poisoning of her husband Beorhtric [be-oh-trik]. This man, the primary source for the Battle of Ashdown, helped his patron translate Pope Gregory I’s (20 pts)",
        "Pastoral Care, which became the oldest extant book written in English. This man’s most famous work documented the subject’s defeat of Guthrum, creation of the (10 pts)",
        "Danelaw, and rule as King of Wessex. For ten points, name this Welsh bishop who wrote the biography Life of King Alfred."
      ],
      "answer": "Bishop Asser"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This phrase describes the genre of A.E. Housman’s poem “From far, from eve and morning.” One form of this phrase titles a novel in which Dr. Tamkin cons Tommy Wilhelm out of his life savings in the stock market; that novel was written by (20 pts)",
        "Saul Bellow. This phrase, which first appeared in book one of (10 pts)",
        "Ovid’s Odes, describes poems like Robert Herrick’s “To the Virgins, to Make Much of Time” and Andrew Marvell’s “To His Coy Mistress.” For ten points, give this Latin phrase that translates to “seize the day.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Carpe Diem",
        "Seize the Day before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The president who authorized this agreement wrote a letter outlining his diplomatic strategy to Governor James Gerrard of Kentucky. Fran¸cois de Barb´e-Marbois [bar-bay mar-bwah] was a key negotiator of this agreement, which arose after an (20 pts)",
        "insurrection on Saint Domingue [sahn doh-meeng]. Talleyrand objected to this plan, which resulted in the (10 pts)",
        "Lewis and Clark Expedition surveying its central land area. The size of the United States was doubled by, for ten points, what 1803 purchase of French land under Thomas Jefferson?"
      ],
      "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work, this philosopher wrote that “the self is a relation which relates itself to its own self,” and in another work he wrote “subjectivity is truth.” This thinker, who envisioned the aesthetic, ethical, and religious modes of life, had a quarrel with the Corsair satirical newspaper that led him to drop his use of (20 pts)",
        "pseudonyms. The terms “infinite resignation” and “knight of faith” were coined by this man in a work that examines (10 pts)",
        "Abraham’s binding of Isaac. For ten points, name this Danish existentialist thinker who wrote Fear and Trembling and Either/Or."
      ],
      "answer": "Soren Kierkegaard"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Cricketer John Thayer died during this event, but Milton Hershey didn’t due to an urgent need to attend to business affairs. This event, which Stanley Lord failed to respond to, is the subject of Thomas Hardy’s poem “The (20 pts)",
        "Convergence of the Twain.” The Carpathia led rescue efforts during this event, in which (10 pts)",
        "Molly Brown ordered Lifeboat 6 to look for survivors. For ten points, name this April 1912 maritime disaster involving an iceberg and an “unsinkable” ocean liner."
      ],
      "answer": "sinking of the RMS Titanic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s speech at the University of Kansas stated that the gross domestic product “measures everything except that which is worthwhile.” This man, who cited a man who gave a “ripple of hope” to South Africa in his “Day of (20 pts)",
        "Affirmation” speech, wrote the book The Enemy Within about his efforts fighting the Teamsters in court. This politician was trailing (10 pts)",
        "Eugene McCarthy in the presidential primaries when Sirhan Sirhan assassinated him in Los Angeles. For ten points, name this man who served as attorney general under his brother John."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Robert Francis Kennedy",
        "Bobby Kennedy",
        "RFK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ermolao Barbaro praised a book by this man but noted that it contained over five thousand pieces of scientifically inaccurate information. Upon seeing a phenomenon that looked “like an umbrella pine,” this man journeyed from Misenum to (20 pts)",
        "rescue Rectina and Pomponianus. Although this man remarked that “fortune favors the brave,” his corpse was (10 pts)",
        "excavated from pumice at Stabiae. Letters to Tactius from this man’s nephew detail his death during the eruption of Mount Vesuvius. For ten points, name this Roman scientist, the author of Natural History."
      ],
      "answer": "Pliny the Elder"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author discussed the election of Donald Trump in the essay “Mourning for Whiteness.” This author’s hometown of Lorain, Ohio is the setting of her debut novel, in which marigolds ominously fail to bloom and (20 pts)",
        "Pecola longs for the title symbol of whiteness. In the aftermath of the Whitewater scandal, this author described Bill Clinton as the first black president. (10 pts)",
        "Escaped slave Margaret Garner inspired a novel by this author in which a murdered baby returns from the Ohio River as a ghost. For ten points, name this American Nobel laureate who wrote The Bluest Eye and Beloved."
      ],
      "answer": "Toni Morrison or Chloe Anthony Wofford Morrison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An author from this country was imprisoned for writing the article “Thoughts on March 8,” which criticized this country’s leaders for leaving their wives. Another author from this country wrote the novels To Live and (20 pts)",
        "Brothers, which depict struggle sessions in this country. Another author from this country wrote the novel (10 pts)",
        "Red Sorghum, which ends with a war between this country and Japan. For ten points, name this home country of Ding Ling, Yu Hua, and Mo Yan, who depicted this country’s revolution under Mao Zedong."
      ],
      "answer": "People’s Republic of China or Zhongguo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man is portrayed in the film International Guerillas as plotting to cause the downfall of Pakistan by opening casinos and discos. This man's memoir Joseph Anton details his time living in hiding. In one novel, this (20 pts)",
        "author depicted a woman who eats butterflies leading a pilgrimage into the Arabian Sea. In another novel, this man fictionalized the Emergency as a time when children born near the time of (10 pts)",
        "Indian independence were arrested. For ten points, name this British-Indian author, who received death threats for writing The Satanic Verses."
      ],
      "answer": "Salman Rushdie"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Orders by this man led to the murder of translator Hitoshi Igarashi. Nader Naderpour often recited poetry with this man whose disciple, Morteza Motahhari, founded the Combatant Clergy Association. This man's opposition to the White Revolution led the (*) Shah to send troops to Qom [[GOHM]], and this man's house arrest led to the 15 Khordad Uprising. This man regularly called the U.S. the \"Great Satan\" and published a fatwa calling for (*) Salman Rushdie's murder. Having gained national popularity through the Iran Hostage Crisis, for ten points, who was this Ayatollah?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author depicted a legendary noblewoman who sold her soul to feed her tenants in the verse drama The Countess Cathleen. This author was inspired by a childhood trip to Lough [[LOCK]] Gill to write a poem about wanting to return to a \"small cabin… of clay and wattles made.\" Along with Edward (20 pts)",
        "Martyn and Lady Gregory, this author founded the Abbey Theatre. This poet reflected on a failed uprising against British rule in the poem (10 pts)",
        "\"Easter, 1916.\" For ten points, name this Irish poet, the author of “Sailing to Byzantium” and “The Second Coming.\""
      ],
      "answer": "William Butler Yeats"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Though it was written for publication in The New York Times Magazine, this document was not published there despite protests from editor Harvey Shapiro. This document was written in response to “A Call (20 pts)",
        "for Unity,\" an open letter by white clergymen referring to this document's author as an \"outsider.\" Claiming \"injustice anywhere is a threat to justice everywhere,\" (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, which open letter was written from a cell by Martin Luther King Jr.?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Letter from Birmingham Jail",
        "Letter from Birmingham City Jail",
        "or The Negro Is Your Brother"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A memoir set during this war titled Storm of Steel was written by Ernst Jünger [[YUHN-ger]], the youngest ever winner of the Pour le Mérite [[meh-REET]]. Barbara Tuchman wrote a Pulitzer Prize-winning historiography of this war titled The Guns (20 pts)",
        "of August. Winston Churchill published The World Crisis concerning this war, including his own failures during its Dardanelles Campaign at (10 pts)",
        "Gallipoli. For ten points, name this early 20th-century war whose literary masterpieces include All Quiet on the Western Front."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "World War One",
        "the Great War",
        "WWI"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The poet of Morgante, Luigi Pulci [[PUHL-chi]], wrote a verse poem celebrating this nobleman's victory in a 1469 jousting tournament. To acquire the support of this man, Sultan Qaitbay presented him with a (20 pts)",
        "giraffe which this man let roam the city streets, according to poet Antonio Costanzo. This politician survived an assassination attempt during the Pazzi Conspiracy, an act sanctioned by the sitting Pope and rival of his family (10 pts)",
        "Sixtus IV. For ten points, name this \"Magnificent\" ruler of Florence, the grandson of Cosimo."
      ],
      "answer": "Lorenzo de' Medici"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote a romanticized account of the Covenanters victory at Loudon Hill in his novel Old Mortality. The lynching of the title man in the historical Porteous [[POHR-shus]] Riots in Edinburgh acts as the backdrop for this man's novel, (20 pts)",
        "The Heart of the Midlothian. In another novel by this man, the title Anglo-Saxon pretends to be the Spanish knight Desdichado to win a (10 pts)",
        "tournament presided over by King John. Rowena is married to the title knight at the behest of Richard the Lionheart in, for ten points, what author's novel Ivanhoe?"
      ],
      "answer": "Walter Scott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was sent to work oversees by the publication El Espectador after he publicized government misdeeds in his work The Story of a Shipwrecked Sailor. The United Fruit Company's 1928 massacre of banana plantation (20 pts)",
        "workers in Santa Maria inspired an episode in one of this man's novels, in which the only survivor is José Arcadio Segundo, a member of the (10 pts)",
        "Buendia [[bwehn-DEE-ah]] family. The town of Macondo and its environs were inspired by, for ten points, which author's homeland of Colombia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Gabriel Garcia Marquez"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his Epigrams, the writer Martial records how this man banned male castration despite having the eunuch Earinus as a lover. Before being called back by this emperor to fight in the Dacian [[dah-KEE-ehn]] war, the governor Gnaeus Julius (20 pts)",
        "Agricola led a failed conquest of Caledonia after conquering modern Wales. The courtier Parthinus likely led the 96 AD plot to assassinate this emperor, who was succeeded by the elder statesman (10 pts)",
        "Nerva. The last emperor of the Flavian dynasty was, for ten points, which authoritarian emperor?"
      ],
      "answer": "Domitian or Domitianus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote on the common misconceptions and poor arguments primarily used by MPs in the British Parliament in his work The Book of Fallacies. Per his will, this man was made into an (20 pts)",
        "\"auto-icon,\" basically a preserved corpse, which is still on display at the University College-London. This man theorized a (10 pts)",
        "prison where a single guard can see every interned prisoner at once. For ten points, name this formulator of the Panopticon, the father of utilitarianism."
      ],
      "answer": "Jeremy Bentham"
    }
  ]
}